<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Photography on Chris Smith</title>
    <link>http://crsmithdev.com/categories/photography/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Photography on Chris Smith</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2016 21:00:11 +0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://crsmithdev.com/categories/photography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Yushima Tenman-gū</title>
      <link>http://crsmithdev.com/blog/yushima-tenman-gu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2016 21:00:11 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://crsmithdev.com/blog/yushima-tenman-gu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://crsmithdev.com/images/yushima-shrine.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yushima_Tenman-g%C5%AB&#34;&gt;Yushima Tenman-gū&lt;/a&gt; is a small Shinto shrine in northern Tokyo I found after getting off at the wrong train station on the way to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ueno_Park&#34;&gt;Ueno Park&lt;/a&gt;.  The building pictured above is actually not the main shrine itself, but one of the other buildings in the complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yushima_Tenman-g%C5%AB&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yushima Tenman-gū Shrine (湯島天満宮) is a Shinto shrine in Tokyo, Japan devoted to Tenjin, the Kami of Learning. It is located in the Bunkyo ward of Tokyo, not far from the University of Tokyo, and is a frequent site of prospective students hoping to pass the entrance exams there in April. At this time, the temple receives many offerings of ema votives to petition the kami for success at exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also ran into this content-looking little guy at the shrine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://crsmithdev.com/images/yushima-bull.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Mode Gakuen Cocoon Tower</title>
      <link>http://crsmithdev.com/blog/mode-gakuen-cocoon-tower/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2016 11:47:20 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://crsmithdev.com/blog/mode-gakuen-cocoon-tower/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://crsmithdev.com/images/mode-gakuen.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite buildings in Tokyo is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mode_Gakuen_Cocoon_Tower&#34;&gt;Mode Gakuen Cocoon Tower&lt;/a&gt;.  Located in Shinjuku, it&amp;rsquo;s one of the most striking buildings on the skyline.  The above is shot from an unusual angle, looking up from an opening in the pedestrian tunnel that leads west from the station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mode_Gakuen_Cocoon_Tower&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before selecting a design for its new Tokyo location, Mode Gakuen held a competition asking architects to submit design proposals for the building. The only condition was that the building could not be rectangular. Mode Gakuen received more than 150 proposals by approximately 50 architects. The winning proposal was a cocoon-like structure designed by Tange Associates. According to Tange Associates the building&amp;rsquo;s cocoon shape symbolizes a building that nurtures the students inside. White aluminum and dark blue glass exterior form the structure&amp;rsquo;s curved shell, which is criss-crossed by a web of white diagonal lines earning it the name &amp;ldquo;Cocoon Tower&amp;rdquo;. A Tange Associates spokesperson stated that their aim was to use the building to revitalize the surrounding area and to create a gateway between Shinjuku Station and the Shinjuku central business district. The building&amp;rsquo;s design earned the firm the Emporis.com 2008 Skyscraper of the year award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>